<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title>jaca's safe haven</title>
        <description>Updates from jaca's safe haven</description>
        <language>en</language>
        <link>https://jacadzaca.github.io/rss.xml</link>
        <atom:link href="https://jacadzaca.github.io/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
        <image>
            <title>jaca's safe haven</title>
            <url>https://jacadzaca.github.io//pix/avatar.jpg</url>
            <link>https://jacadzaca.github.io/rss.xml</link>
        </image>
            <item>
                <title>hacking a warcraft 3 map</title>
                <guid>https://jacadzaca.github.io/blog/hacking_a_warcraft_3_map.html</guid>
                <link>https://jacadzaca.github.io/blog/hacking_a_warcraft_3_map.html</link>
                <pubDate>Wed, 29 Dec 2021 16:15:35 0200</pubDate>
                <description>
                    <![CDATA[ 

        <p>
            I'm a big Warcraft fan. Actually, I consider Warcraft 3 to be the best video game of all time. I like the story, the voice-acting (polish voice-over was great until Reforged), and
            the music fits game-play. But what's best about Warcraft 3 is its universal game engine that combined with the powerful game editor would lead to creation of many unique mods. Of course, I have my favorite:
            a polish modification called <i>Alchemicy</i> - a combination of a hero defense and a crafting game. Although the mod is loads of fun, one aspect of it always bugged me: there are characters that you can only play as after
            either making a donation to the author or if you know him in-game. What's more, the donation service was <a target="_blank" href="https://warrttssgames.blogspot.com/p/premium-alchemicy.html">shut-down in 2012</a> with the guy quting the game. Since the map is protected,
            meaning nobody can open the mod file in the editor, the characters seemed to have been lost to the sands of time... Until I figured out a way to produce a patch that removes the paywall.
        </p>

        <h2>Protections, how do they work?</h2>
        <p>
            First, a brief introduction to the Warcraft map file format (w3x). For my purposes, every Warcraft 3 mod is basically an archive (<a target="_blank" href="https://world-editor-tutorials.thehelper.net/cat_usersubmit.php?view=42787">see here for proper docs</a>) that contains
            <a target="_blank" href="https://github.com/ChiefOfGxBxL/WC3MapTranslator#file-support">a few files</a>, each relating to different aspects of the mod. <a target="_blank" href="http://www.3ice.hu/blog/protect-warcraft-maps/#delete">Certain files</a> (from now on - <em>header files</em>)
            only carry data that's required by the game editor to open up the map, other files are mandatory (for example, the map file), there also might be some auxiliary files; most probably custom models, icons or sounds. What's crucial is that each file contains information that
            allows a human to identify it (e.g, the file defining custom units contains units' names, hitpoints etc.)
            <p>
                All map protection software dose is remove the header files, therefore making the editor crush each time you try to open a protected map with it.
                It also removes the MPQ's (name of the archiving format) listfile, therefore obfuscating files' names.
            </p>
        </p>

        <h2>The plan</h2>
        <p>
            Since I'm familiar with the Warcraft ecosystem, a glance at the map in-game revealed that there must be a certain upgrade that
            is granted to all 'premium' users. Since all of the custom upgrades are in the <i>war3map.w3q</i> file, I figured that all I need to do
            is:
            <ol>
                <li>identify the .w3q file</li>
                <li>byte patch the mod-file directly or:</li>
                    <ol type="i">
                        <li>convert the file into editable form</li>
                        <li>make applicable changes</li>
                        <li>convert the file back and patch the mod-file using an editor</li>
                    </ol>
            </ol>
            Sadly, this approach doesn't work, because:
            <ol>
                <li>files in the MPQ are somehow compressed, so you cannot byte-patch them directly</li>
                <li>the MPQ's listfile is gone, so you cannot add new files. You cannot replace a file without adding a file</li>
                <li>the .w3q files only cotains the upgrade's definition (ID, description etc). The correct place to apply the patch is in the <i>war3map.w3u</i> file</li>
            </ol>
            Luckily, the new insight allowed me to conjure an approach that works:
            <ol>
                <li>acquire a Warcraft map with a listfile - a template</li>
                <li>extract and identify the files inside the <i>Alchemicy</i> mod file</li>
                <li>make applicable changes to the <i>war3map.w3u</i> file</li>
                <li>replace the files inside the template with the ones extracted</li>
            </ol>
            We are going to need:
            <ol>
                <li>the <a target="_blank" href="http://www.zezula.net/en/mpq/download.html">MPQ editor</a> (it runs under Wine) to both extract, and overwrite files found in a .w3x file</li>
                <li><a target="_blank" href="https://github.com/ChiefOfGxBxL/WC3MapTranslator/tree/v1.1.0">this w3x parser</a> to identify the files</li>
                <li><a download href="https://www.epicwar.com/maps/download/231379/688fa38f47c622d9e3e3afddb95520c5a2a4707c64c5ec23c5ee994b1e3826f461c63b9f/Alchemicy%203.22v.w3x"><i>Alchemicy</i> map file</a></li>
                <li>a 128 by 128, <i>Cityscape</i> tileset, Warcraft map to use as a template</li>
            </ol>
        </p>

        <h2>The implementation</h2>
        <p>
            First, I downloaded one of my old, unfinished maps for a template. Then, I created two directories:
            <i>identified-files</i> and <i>unidentified-files</i> and extracted all files from the map (save for .blp and .mdx files) into the second one. Second, I noticed that it's possible to
            identify few of the files just by either looking at them or by opening them in your <a target="_blank" href="https://neovim.io/">favorite text editor</a>:
            <ol>
                <li>since File00000000.w3e has an extension, it's probably the war3map.w3e file</li>
                <li>by comparsion with your template map, File00000001.xxx is the war3map.w3i file</li>
                <li>since File00000002.xxx is fillied with strings, it must be the war3map.wts file</li>
                <li>since File00000003.xxx looks like computer code, it must be the war3map.j file</li>
                <li>since File00000007.wpm has an extension, it's probably the war3map.wpm file</li>
                <li>the File0000000008.doo is either the the war3map.doo or the war3mapUnits.doo</li>
                <li>by comparsion with your template map, File00000015.xxx is the war3mapMisc.txt file</li>
                <li>by comparsion with your template map, File00000016.xxx is the war3mapExtra.txt file</li>
            </ol>
            I renamed the identified files and moved them into the other directory. I also ran <a target="_blank" href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/ChiefOfGxBxL/WC3MapTranslator/v1.1.0/examples/jsonToWar/entity/doodads.js">this example script</a>
            that is provided by the parser to figure out that the .doo file is the war3Map.doo file. Nearly all other files can be identified using <a target="_blank" href="https://gist.githubusercontent.com/jacadzaca/9f094f8aa8131278a375f5d96caeb748/raw/4be413027c1444b3e9ebf27d6306258371e05cd5/check.sh">this script</a>,
            after applying this 'patch' inside the <i>WC3MapTranslator/examples/warToJson</i> directory:
            <p>
                <code>
                    find . -name '*js' -exec sed -i -e 's|fs.writeFileSync(jsonPath, |console.log(|g' {} \;
                </code>
            </p>
             File00000004, File00000006 and File00000012 couldn't be parsed into anything sensible. I would later figure out that
             (using a method of trail and error) File00000004 is the .shd file and that File00000006 is the .mmp file. I couldn't figure what File00000012 is.
            <p>
                Thirdly, I would convert both the <a target="_blank" href="">.w3q</a> and the <a target="_blank" href="">.w3u file</a> into JSON and compare them:
            </p>
            <hr>
            <a target="_blank" href="/pix/json_comparison.png"><img loading="lazy" alt="a side-by-side comparision of JSON representation of the .w3q and .w3u" title="a side-by-side comparision of JSON representation of the .w3q and .w3u" src="/pix/json_comparison.png"></a>
            <hr>
            I figured that the simplest solution would be to blank-out the <i>value</i> record with:
            <p>
                <code>
                    sed -i -e 's|R000||g' units.json
                </code>
            </p>
            Then, I would convert the edited <a target="_blank" href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/ChiefOfGxBxL/WC3MapTranslator/v1.1.0/examples/jsonToWar/object/units.js">JSON back into a .w3u file</a>
            and continue as planned.
        </p>
        <h2>Conclusions</h2>
        <p>
            Although the patch works (see [1]), it's somehow rough around (points [2-5]) the edges:
            <hr>
            <a target="_blank" href="/pix/hero_selection_comparison.png"><img loading="lazy" alt="a side-by-side comparison of original Alchemicy map and its 'hacked' version" title="a side-by-side comparison of original Alchemicy map and its 'hacked' version" src="/pix/hero_selection_comparison.png"></a>
            <hr>
            I also think it's also worth mentioning that:
            <ol>
                <li>although my way of identifying the files works, it turns out that <a target="_blank" href="http://www.zezula.net/en/mpq/war3maps.html">MPQ Editor</a> automates this process.</li>
                <li>although the patched map can be opened in the editor, the game crushes when I try to launch the map</li>
                <li>there exist <a target="_blank" href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=98nXuBiKVig">a program</a> that can automate the whole process, but:</li>
                <ol type="i">
                    <li>it's literally a sketchy, Russian program from the internet</li>
                    <li>I've never seen any explanation of it's inner workings</li>
                </ol>
                <li>I later used the MPQ Editor's <i>Name Scanner</i> feature to fix issues [2-5], it turns out that:</li>
                <ol type="i">
                    <li>File00000016 is actually war3mapSkin.txt - renaming the file fixes [2] and [4]</li>
                    <li>one of the .blp files was the wa3mapMap.blp - including this file in the patch fixes [3]</li>
                    <li>other .blp and .mdx files were custom models/icons - including them in the patch fixes [5]</li>
                </ol>
                <li><i>warcraft3mapUnit.doo</i> is a header file</li>
            </ol>
        </p>
         ]]>
                </description>
            </item>
            <item>
                <title>are landlords cringe</title>
                <guid>https://jacadzaca.github.io/blog/are_landlords_cringe.html</guid>
                <link>https://jacadzaca.github.io/blog/are_landlords_cringe.html</link>
                <pubDate>Wed, 22 Dec 2021 19:04:05 0200</pubDate>
                <description>
                    <![CDATA[ 
            I've noticed that the contempt for <a target="_blank" href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=6fBA2CBurVg">landlords</a> (<a target="_blank" href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=mDfRl6dJcYI">example in polish</a>)
            has recently reached a new level - landlord being are equated with social parasites, who are going to cause an <a target="_blank" href="https://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2018/apr/16/landlords-social-parasites-last-people-should-be-honouring-buy-to-let">overpopulation crisis in literal hell</a>.
            Surely, behind such brutal rhetoric stands some merit?
            <h2>Landlords bad!1!1!</h2>
            <p>
                Landlords are said not to do any work - they just siphon others' efforts. If you and your landlord earn a similar wage and you're both saving for a new flat, it's going to be your landlord that can buy it first, although they already have a place of their own. Albeit, a landlord makes sure your apartment is a decent place to live (e.g they call in a plumber once in a while)
                it doesn't lessens their parasitism, because then they become a <a target="_blank" href="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/d/df/We_Can_Do_It%21_NARA_535413_-_Restoration_2.jpg/463px-We_Can_Do_It%21_NARA_535413_-_Restoration_2.jpg">redundant middleman</a> (it's not rocket science to call a plumber).
                Some might claim that becoming a landlord actually requires much effort - you must take risk, familiarize yourself with the appropriate laws, go around searching for a property etc. but why someone should bother with it all? Can't we
                organize into housing cooperatives or establish a government monopoly on rentiership and thus socialize the trouble?
            </p>
            <h2>Landlords bad?</h2>
            <p>
                Imagine you're moving into city of Ekslandia - let's say you've landed a job opportunity there. You're pretty sure that you won't stay in Ekslandia for more than N years. Sadly, all of the established housing cooperatives are already full (they provide high quality housing, so nobody want to leave)
                and the ongoing initiatives either will take more than N years to provide you with a quarter (establishing an organization is not a timely process) or are not welcoming of total strangers that hardly have a job in the city (<a target="_blank" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Housing_cooperative">housing coops are allowed to select who's to live with them</a>). You try applying for social housing, but it turns out that it favors people with turbulent past.
                Running out of options (and since people on the internet told you that all landlords do is exploit), you want to take out a loan and buy an apartment. You meet up with your financial adviser and he tells you that the loan over the N years that you plan to stay in the city will cost you X, however he also mentions that
                due to the growth of available housing alternatives, the typical rent has fallen drastically and it wouldn't be hard to find a similar apartment that over the next N years will only cost you (X - 1). Since everyone can subtract, you quickly figure out that by renting you could actually save one unit of value... Since when does being exploited saves you money?
            </p>
            <h2>Landlord good???</h2>
            <p>
            Although the above story lays down a rather specific scenario (all 'better' options are unavailable, <a target="_blank" href="https://www.nerdwallet.com/mortgages/rent-vs-buy-calculator">renting is cheaper</a> etc.) and thus is not very convincing,
            it's still a scenario that seems to presume most of the skeptics' propositions, while allowing a landlord to contribute to a society. Basically, what a landlord does is allowing the tenant not to buy an apartment; if we were to let go of some skeptics' tenets, e.g that
            housing coops are <em>always</em> more economically efficient, we could ask whether the landlord doesn't produce value by elevating the tenant from the chore of attending coop's board meetings? Surly, if someone is attending a board meeting they are not, for example, spending time with their family.
            Summarizing, we cannot conclude whether landlords are cringe and useless <em>ex offico</em> - when a landlord grants you affordable accommodation they are not cringe otherwise they probably are.
            </p>
         ]]>
                </description>
            </item>
            <item>
                <title>other way to find sin of 18</title>
                <guid>https://jacadzaca.github.io/blog/other_way_to_find_sin_of_18.html</guid>
                <link>https://jacadzaca.github.io/blog/other_way_to_find_sin_of_18.html</link>
                <pubDate>Tue, 28 Sep 2021 13:43:07 0200</pubDate>
                <description>
                    <![CDATA[ 
        It turns out that you can find the value of sin(18&#176;) by the following method:
        <p>
            Notice that by the sin addition formula:
            <pre>
    1&#176; sin(54&#176;) - sin(18&#176;) = 2 * cos(<sup>(54&#176; + 18&#176;)</sup>&frasl;<sub>2</sub>) * sin(<sup>(54&#176; - 18&#176;)</sup>&frasl;<sub>2</sub>) = 2 * cos(36&#176;) * sin(18&#176;)
            </pre>
            Also:
            <pre>
    sin(54&#176;) - sin(18&#176;) = cos(90&#176; - 54&#176;) - sin(18&#176;) = cos(36&#176;) - sin(18&#176;)
            </pre>
            Moreover, by the double cosine formula:
            <pre>
    2&#176; cos(36&#176;) = cos[(2 * 18)&#176;] = cos<sup>2</sup>(18&#176;) - sin<sup>2</sup>(18&#176;)
            </pre>
            Now use the Pythagorean identity like this:
            <pre>
    cos<sup>2</sup>(18&#176;) - sin<sup>2</sup>(18&#176;) = 1 - sin<sup>2</sup>(18&#176;) - sin<sup>2</sup>(18&#176;) = 1 - 2 * sin<sup>2</sup>(18&#176;)
            </pre>
            Now equate the right-hand side of equation 2&#176; with the right-hand side of statement 1&#176;, and substitute for <i>cos(36&#176;)</i>:
            <pre>
    cos(36&#176;) - sin(18&#176;) = 2 * cos(36&#176;) * sin(18&#176;)
    1 - 2 * sin<sup>2</sup>(18&#176;) - sin(18&#176;) = 2 * [1 - 2 * sin<sup>2</sup>(18&#176;)] * sin(18&#176;) = 2 * sin(18&#176;) - 4 * sin<sup>3</sup>(18&#176;)
    4 * sin<sup>3</sup>(18&#176;) - 2 * sin<sup>2</sup>(18&#176;) - 3 * sin(18&#176;) + 1 = 0
    t := sin(18&#176;)
    4t<sup>3</sup> - 2t<sup>2</sup> - 3t + 1 = 0
            </pre>
            Notice that for t = 1 the equation is satisfied, so:
            <pre>
    4t<sup>3</sup> - 2t<sup>2</sup> - 3t + 1 = (t - 1)(4t<sup>2</sup> + 2t - 1) = 0 &lt;=&gt; t = 1 or 4t<sup>2</sup> + 2t - 1 = 0
    4t<sup>2</sup> + 2t - 1 = 0
    &Delta; = 4 + 4 * 4 = 4 * 5
    &#8730;&Delta; = 2&#8730;5
    t<sub>1</sub> = <sup>(-2 + 2&#8730;5)</sup>&frasl;<sub>8</sub> = <sup>(-1 + &#8730;5)</sup>&frasl;<sub>4</sub>
    t<sub>2</sub> = <sup>(-2 - 2&#8730;5)</sup>&frasl;<sub>8</sub> = <sup>(-1 - &#8730;5)</sup>&frasl;<sub>4</sub>
            </pre>
            Now notice that <i>1 &gt; t &gt; 0</i>, because <i>sin(x)</i> is an increasing function when <i>90 &gt; x &gt; 0</i> and <i>sin(90&#176;) = 1 > sin(18&#176;) > sin(0&#176;) = 0</i>,
            so <i> t = sin(18&#176;) = <sup>(-1 + &#8730;5)</sup>&frasl;<sub>4</sub> </i>, since that's the only solutions that meets the criteria
        </p>
        While this method works, it's not easy to come up with the first equation. I stumbled on it by pure coincidence.
        I personally prefer the <a href="/pix/geo_sin18.png">geometrical</a> way of finding the value of sin(18), because it strikes me as the more obvious way of doing it.
         ]]>
                </description>
            </item>
            <item>
                <title>how sin is computed</title>
                <guid>https://jacadzaca.github.io/blog/how_sin_is_computed.html</guid>
                <link>https://jacadzaca.github.io/blog/how_sin_is_computed.html</link>
                <pubDate>Wed, 18 Aug 2021 14:35:08 0200</pubDate>
                <description>
                    <![CDATA[ 
            I can recall the first time I wrote a program that used a trigonometric function - it
            was back in secondary school. I was making a game and wanted to make some object float around
            another. Back then, I didn't know what trig functions were and how they worked, so I copied
            some code from the web and, to my astonishment, it worked. I got curious how these functions worked, so
            I pressed F3 in my IDE and tried to look for the source code of Math.sin. I can't remember whether I found
            the code and didn't understand it or whether I couldn't find the implementation at all. It doesn't really
            matter. What dose, is that back then I swore to myself that one day I will implement my own sin function.
            Two days ago, I've learned about <a target="_blank" href="https://www.khanacademy.org/math/ap-calculus-bc/bc-series-new#bc-10-11">Taylor Series</a>.
            <p>
            <h2>Taylors, how do they work?</h2>
            Taylor series is a tool to express some function as a polynomial, using its nth derivative.
            Since <i>sin(x)</i> and its derivatives are differentiable, we can express <i>f(x) = sin(x)</i> as:
            <pre>
            p(x) = &sum;<sub>n=0</sub><sup>&infin;</sup>f<sup>(n)</sup>(a) * <sup>(x-a)<sup>n</sup></sup>&frasl;<sub>n!</sub>
            </pre>
            In this case, we can't add infinitely many terms in a finite amount of time, so we have
            to approximate. Since this is a toy implementation, we will just compare it with python's
            math.sin implementation and call it quits when they will converge <i>good enough</i>.
            </p>
            <p>
            <h2>Implementation</h2>
            First, we need some way of obtaining the nth derivative of sin, evaluated at some center <i>a</i>.
            By writing down sin's first fifteen derivatives, we can see that the odd derivatives are either <i>1 * cos(x)</i> or
            <i>(-1) * cos(x)</i>, while the plural ones take the form of 1 * <i>sin(x)</i> or (-1) * <i>sin(x)</i>. What is more difficult
            to see, is that derivatives with an ordinal that yields a reminder of two or three when divided by four are the
            derivatives with and minus sign. I don't know how to formally prove it... <em>yet</em>, but you need to trust me on this one.
            Translating into python code:
            <pre><code>
                def nth_sin_derivative(n, a=math.pi/2):
                    if n % 4 in (2,3):
                        sign = -1
                    else:
                        sign = 1
                    if n % 2 == 0:
                        function = sin
                    else:
                        function = cos
                return sign * function(a)
            </code></pre>

            Second, we need to actually be able to evaluate both <i>cos(x)</i> and <i>sin(x)</i> at our center. Since we are implementing <i>sin(x)</i>,
            we should deal with <i>cos(x)</i> first. We don't have to implement <i>cos(x)</i> separately -  notice that <i>sin(<sup>&#960</sup>&frasl;<sub>2</sub> - x) = cos(x)</i>:
            <code><pre>
                def cos(x):
                    return sin((math.pi/2) - x)
            </code></pre>
            Great. That solves the <i>cos(x)</i> part. Now, we can finally implement <i>sin(x)</i>:
            <code><pre>
            def sin(x, center=math.pi/2, term_count=5):
                if x == math.pi/2:
                    return 1
                elif x == 0:
                    return 0
                else:
                    values = (((x - center)**i / math.factorial(i)) * nth_sin_derivative(i, a=center) for i in range(term_count))
                    return sum(values)
            </code></pre>
            We specify two special cases: <i>x = <sup>&#960</sup>&frasl;<sub>2</sub></i> for evaluating sin derivatives that require to compute <i>sin(x)</i> at center,
            and <i>x = 0</i> for evaluating sin derivatives that require to compute <i>cos(x)</i> at center. Else, we compute the Taylor series.
            </p>
            <p>
            <h2>Is the implementation any good?</h2>
            Well, it sure can compute <i>sin(x)</i>! With term_count=19 the approximation is nearly as good as the python's
            math.sin:
            <hr>
            <a target="_blank" href="/pix/sin_taylor_series_barplot.gif"><img src="/pix/sin_taylor_series_barplot.gif"></img></a>
            <hr>
            <hr>
            <a target="_blank" href="/pix/sin_taylor_series.gif"><img src="/pix/sin_taylor_series.gif"></img></a>
            <hr>
            However, assemblies actually provide an <a target="_blank" href="https://cs.fit.edu/~mmahoney/cse3101/nasmdocb.html#section-B.4.100">fsin</a> instruction, so
            computing <i>sin(x)</i> in software when speed matters is kinda cringe. On the side note, CPUs don't actually use a Taylor series
            to compute trig functions - they use <a target="_blank" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cordic">CORDIC</a>.
            </p>
            <p>
                <a target="_blank" href="https://gist.github.com/jacadzaca/0b76d75411566d506df3d8897204e00e">Code that generates the graphs</a>
            </p>
         ]]>
                </description>
            </item>
            <item>
                <title>transfer files with netcat</title>
                <guid>https://jacadzaca.github.io/blog/transfer_files_with_netcat.html</guid>
                <link>https://jacadzaca.github.io/blog/transfer_files_with_netcat.html</link>
                <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jul 2021 01:25:29 0200</pubDate>
                <description>
                    <![CDATA[ 

        As I don't use my <a target="_blank" href="/blog/btw_i_use_arch.html">arch laptop</a> that much, I've figured
        that I can use it as a backup storage for my collections - collections of memes and movies.
            <p>
                <h2>Rsync is bloat?</h2>
                Using some kind of a USB as an intermediary wouldn't do the
                trick, because my meme collection is 14GB big (pathetic), whereas my movies
                take 139GB. My first though was to use <a target="_blank" href="https://rsync.samba.org/examples.html">rsync</a>.
                I've never used rsync before, so I perused its man page and quickly found out that you can use:
                <pre>
<code>rsync -vzP /some/path user@remote:/some/other/path</code>
                </pre>
                to sync the files. Then... I got a ssh error. I couldn't be bothered to install a ssh server on
                my laptop, because that would only bloat my precious <em><strong>Arch</strong></em> Linux install. I continued the search.
            </p>
            <p>
                <h2>Rsync is bloat, so let's pipe stuff into some program</h2>
                I've <a target="_blank" href="https://superuser.com/questions/153176/how-to-rsync-a-large-file-with-as-little-cpu-and-bandwidth-expense-as-possible#answer-1020737">stumbled on this</a>
                StackOverflow answer. Not only does this guy have a method that would allow me to transfer my movies without installing a ssh server, but he also claims that it's faster
                (rsync shines more when it comes to syncing
                <a target="_blank" href="https://fedoramagazine.org/copying-large-files-with-rsync-and-some-misconceptions/">files that are 'similar'</a>).
                It turns out that you can compress the files with tar and then use netcat to send them over the network with:
                <pre>
<code>tar -cpv --atime-preserve=system /path/to/ | nc -q 10 -l -p 45454</code>
                </pre>
                on the source machine, and
                <pre>
<code>nc -w 10 X.X.X.X 45454 | tar -xpv</code>
                </pre>
                on the destination computer. The traffic isn't encrypted at all, but that's not a problem over LAN (e.g sending movies
                to my laptop). Albeit, <a target="_blank" href="https://screenage.de/blog/2007/12/30/using-netcat-and-tar-for-network-file-transfer/#comment-35">encryption can be provided with ssh</a> or 
                <a target="_blank" href="https://screenage.de/blog/2007/12/30/using-netcat-and-tar-for-network-file-transfer/#comment-936">with a VPN</a>.
            </p>
        I think this method is very linux-like, because it combines two programs in some unusual fashion to create something new. I might consider replacing
        <a target="_blank" href="https://www.man7.org/linux/man-pages/man1/scp.1.html">scp</a> with the ssh version of this trick.
         ]]>
                </description>
            </item>
            <item>
                <title>my calendar system</title>
                <guid>https://jacadzaca.github.io/blog/my_calendar_system.html</guid>
                <link>https://jacadzaca.github.io/blog/my_calendar_system.html</link>
                <pubDate>Fri, 18 Jun 2021 23:42:06 0200</pubDate>
                <description>
                    <![CDATA[ 
        <b>TL;DR</b>: I spend too much time on the Internet, should find some <a target="_blank" href="https://www.urbandictionary.com/define.php?term=fren">frens</a> and go out more lol?
            <p>
                Over the past three years, I've developed this odd habit of writing down <b>everything</b>
                I do in my calendar. I've developed the habit mostly out of curiosity: I wanted to know how much
                time I spend on the Internet, playing video games, programming etc. Besides, I'm rather sentimental.
            </p>
            <p>
                Last week, I realized that having one calendar doesn't actually allow me to do that, because each
                event has a unique name (e.g if a play some video concrete game I write down that I'm playing concretely it).
                That means that running some <em>simple</em> script, on the calendar, to sum the events' durations
                would not be plausible (just imagine the regex!). I should have several calendars, so that I
                could sort each event in to its proper category.
            </p>
            <p>
                <h2>Categories</h2>
                Coming up with the categories turned out to be more difficult that I've anticipated.
                They should be both not too specific, yet not too broad, so the 'time spent on X statistic' wouldn't
                be complete bullocks.
                Should working out be considered its own category, or should I just put it under the 'necessary,
                cannot live without it, but boring' label? Is distro-hopping programming related?
                Should competitive programming be considered as studying or as programming? In the end, I've converged on these ten different categories:
                <ul>
                    <li>relaxing (basically every time, when I don't do anything 'productive' and don't browse the Internet)</li>
                    <li>studying (that includes reading books; dose not include homework)</li>
                    <li>programming (includes distro-hopping and such)</li>
                    <li>chores (includes homework, working, being at, going to and coming back from school, shopping etc.)</li>
                    <li>social (includes writing emails)</li>
                    <li>internet (does NOT include responsible usage; e.g. looking up public transport info)</li>
                    <li>games (video games, not board games or whatever - that goes into social)</li>
                    <li>movies (watching them, NOT going to cinema - that's social... sometimes)</li>
                    <li>blog</li>
                    <li>life (the 'necessary, cannot live without it, but boring' category. Does include working out, because my life quality would decrease without it)</li>
                </ul>
                Splitting the calendar (nearly 10k events) proved to be impossible by hand; wrote a <a target="_blank" href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/jacadzaca/ical-utils/main/split_calendar.py">script</a> for it.
                I concur that some events that should be in the 'chores' category landed in the 'life' category, but only pedants would notice that.
            </p>
            <p>
                <h2>Results</h2>
                <a target="_blank" href="/pix/calendar.png"><img src="/pix/calendar.png"></img></a>
                <p>
                Basically, over the last three years I've spent around 36.8% of my time on mindless Internet browsing, while allocating
                about 2.3% of it to being 'off the grid' (relaxing + social).
                On the other hand, I've used about 37% of my time on doing useful stuff (i.e programming, studying/reading and chores; the number goes down to 22.7%, if
                doing chores would NOT to be included).
                </p>
            </p>
            <p>
                <h2>Conclusion</h2>
                Well, it's kind of problematic to draw conclusion from my 'experiment', because... I have no clue what the average might be.
                How can I tell if I'm doing 'good', whether I'm spending too much (or too little?) time on the Internet, studying etc?
                Besides, the <a target="_blank" href="https://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/antecedent">antecedent</a> (that's literally the fanciest word I know)
                presupposes that the average even exist or is possible to 'compute'! Nonetheless, I surely should try leaving my basement more often, because with that 2.3% staying constant I will
                either lose eyesight or die from vitamin D deficiency - not going outside is surely not <a target="_blank" href="https://www.urbandictionary.com/define.php?term=Lindy&page=2">lindy</a>.
                I also like how calendaring makes me think about my life - when you go on to write down yet another five hour long mindless Internet browsing session, you kinda start to doubt your life decisions lol.
                It kinda functions like Benjamin Franklin's <a target="_blank" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Benjamin_Franklin#Thirteen_Virtues">13 Virtues</a> [<a target="_blank" href="https://daringtolivefully.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/06/13-virtues-chart.jpg">sample chart</a>]
            </p>
         ]]>
                </description>
            </item>
            <item>
                <title>btw i use arch</title>
                <guid>https://jacadzaca.github.io/blog/btw_i_use_arch.html</guid>
                <link>https://jacadzaca.github.io/blog/btw_i_use_arch.html</link>
                <pubDate>Sun, 23 May 2021 15:29:14 0200</pubDate>
                <description>
                    <![CDATA[ 
        I've finally got around to installing Arch Linux on my laptop.
        Installing Arch was simple enough, the only problem that I've had
        was understanding the difference between a boot partition and a
        'boot partition'. A BIOS boot partition is a type of a partition, whereas
        a 'boot partition' is a partition you create for your /boot/ directory -
        you don't actually need a 'boot partition', while a boot partition
        is more or less required - manually telling your boot loader
        (most likely GRUB) where everything is located is way too tedious.
            <p>
            <h2>Programs I run</h2>
            The first thing that I installed was GNOME3. I run GNOME on my
            Ubuntu desktop and it works just fine, I especially like the DE; it
            looks nice out of the box and the Activities tab is amazing. But
            that's mutter36 (mutter is the GNOME DE). mutter40 is nothing like it.
            As of now I run <a href="https://wiki.archlinux.org/title/Xfce">xfce4</a>
            on my laptop and it's alright, albeit a little retro. Actually, xfce's so
            vintage that it might be the best desktop environment for
            an eldery person, but that's neither here or there.
            I'm actually thinking of switching to <a href="https://dwm.suckless.org/">
            dwm</a> or <a href="https://i3wm.org/">i3</a>, but I'm yet
            to decide which one is better. For the login manager I've chosen
            LightDM - it just worked.
            </p>
            <p>
            I don't run <a href="https://developer.gnome.org/NetworkManager/stable/NetworkManager.html">NetworkManager</a>, because
            I have no need for it - just connecting to wi-fi with <a href="https://wiki.archlinux.org/title/Iwd">iwd</a>
            and running a dhcpcd daemon in the background works for me. I also
            installed an <a href="https://github.com/J-Lentz/iwgtk">iwd frontend program</a>,
            because some normal person might have to input a wi-fi password into my
            laptop someday.
            </p>
            <p>
            I use <a href="https://wiki.archlinux.org/title/Udisks">udisks</a> with
            <a href="https://man.archlinux.org/man/community/udiskie/udiskie.8.en">udiskie</a>
            for automating USB mounting. I also run gvfs, so I can have a Trash bin (which
            is less useful than I've thought). gvfs also seems to provide an
            alternative to <a href="https://wiki.archlinux.org/title/Insync">insync</a>, but
            it remains unclear whether you can actually use gvfs effectively without all the
            GNOME bloat.
            </p>
            <p>
            I use <a href="https://wiki.archlinux.org/title/CUPS">CUPS</a> directly
            for printer manging. I even have a desktop shortcut to a
            <a href="https://www.mankier.com/1/chromium-browser#--app">chromium app</a>
            that starts the CUPS web gui.
            </p>
            <p>
            I also considered installing a cron-like program (most probably <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anacron">anacron</a>)
            and running a simple pacman update script, but after a little <a href="https://bbs.archlinux.org/viewtopic.php?id=83118">
                research</a>, I've decided to postpone creating such cron job.
            If after a while of updating nothing breaks, I will surely consider it.
            </p>
            <p>
            <h2>Final thoughts</h2>
            As of now, Arch Linux is my favourite distro; it boots faster than
            Ubuntu, it eats a lot less RAM (which is cool, becouse now I can
            brag on the internet about how little memory my setup needs) and the
            package manager seems to be full of useful programs, especially
            compared to apt. Also, there's AUR, which looks like a both more
            managable and faster version of snap,
            </p>
         ]]>
                </description>
            </item>
            <item>
                <title>psa use vimium</title>
                <guid>https://jacadzaca.github.io/blog/psa_use_vimium.html</guid>
                <link>https://jacadzaca.github.io/blog/psa_use_vimium.html</link>
                <pubDate>Sun, 25 Apr 2021 00:17:08 0200</pubDate>
                <description>
                    <![CDATA[ 
            <p>
            Aren't you tired of having to use your mouse in order to click a link?
            Of course you are, but worry no more - there exists a remedy.
            </p>
            <p>
                <a href="https://github.com/philc/vimium">Vimium</a> is a browser
                (<a href="https://chrome.google.com/webstore/detail/vimium/dbepggeogbaibhgnhhndojpepiihcmeb">download for Chrome</a>,
                 <a href="https://addons.mozilla.org/en-US/firefox/addon/vimium-ff/">download for Firefox</a>)
                 extension that binds all the functionality that you would need to some key combination.
                 You can go to the previous/next page, you can look through your bookmarks, you can
                 even copy the URL of the page you are looking at.
                 <hr>
                 <a href="/pix/vimium.png"><img src="/pix/vimium.png" title="full list of vimium's keybinds"></img></a>
                 <hr>
                 What's also great is the fact that you remap Vimium's key-binds how you like.
            </p>
            <p>
                <h2>Link hints</h2>
                While being able search your bookmarks etc. is all fun and games, all Vimium's feature pale in comparison
                to link hints. By default, pressing ctrl-f will make little boxes with letters (called link hints)
                appear next to all the links on the web-page. You now are only (at most) two key-strokes away from
                <b>clicking</b> that link!
                <hr>
                <video controls>
                    <source src="/pix/vimium.mp4">
                </video>
                <hr>
                You can customize the boxes' look with CSS, however the feature seems to be a little clunky -
                CSS sometimes only loads after refreshing a page.
            </p>
            By the way, I've brought back a <a href="/redpandalore/index.html">ridiculously random site</a> about red pandas.
            I think it was supposed to be a fan-fiction about
            <a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCjdQaSJCYS4o2eG93MvIwqg">Killian</a>,
            but I can't really remeber.
         ]]>
                </description>
            </item>
            <item>
                <title>browser dark mode</title>
                <guid>https://jacadzaca.github.io/blog/browser_dark_mode.html</guid>
                <link>https://jacadzaca.github.io/blog/browser_dark_mode.html</link>
                <pubDate>Sat, 24 Apr 2021 22:04:01 0200</pubDate>
                <description>
                    <![CDATA[ 
            Today I've discovered CSS media queries, one of which has
            especially caught my attention:
            <blockquote>
            <a target="_blank"
             href="https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/CSS/@media/prefers-color-scheme">@media (prefers-color-scheme dark)</a>
            </blockquote>
            Browsers have a built-in dark mode!
            As I am a dark mode <em>connoisseur</em>, I've decided to enable it in my
            browser.
            <p>The first thing that popped into my head was to check the
            <i>chrome://settings/appearance</i>
            page, but it turned out that the theme there was already set to a dark one.
            </p>
            <p>I had to dig deeper.</p>
            After a moment of googling, I've discovered the
            <i>chrome://flags/</i> page,
            where I've found the <i>Web Platform Controls Dark Mode</i> and
            the <i>Force Dark Mode for Web Contents</i> options, which I enabled
            both. The first option was the one I was looking for, but the second was the
            one I was <em>really</em> looking for. It forces <em>every</em> page to
            render in dark mode, to be honest it makes some pages look a little clunky,
            but they are still usable:
            <hr>
            <img style="margin-bottom: 10px" src="/pix/clunky.png" title="there is some white stuff there, yuck!">
            <img src="/pix/clunky1.png" title="the empty levels are not visible, the puppets arms are barely visible">
            <hr>
            <h2>What if I don't use Chrome?</h2>
            During my search, I've also stumbled upon this <a target="_blank" href="https://darkreader.org/">plugin</a>,
            it works with every popular browser, including Chrome (in my opinion though,
            it produces worse looking pages than the naitive option).
         ]]>
                </description>
            </item>
    </channel>
</rss>
